Guide to the James Hazen Hyde Papers 1874-1940, 1953 MS 319
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. General Correspondence, 1878, 1892-1939, 1953; 5.1 Linear feet in 13 boxes and one oversize folder
  - Brisbane, Arthur, 1902-1923 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Brisson, Adolphe & Madeleine, 1910-1928 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Brunetiere, Ferdinand, 1897-1899, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bucher, Pierre (Docteur), 1918-1920 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Byne, Arthur & Mildred, 1921-1934 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Friends living in "backward" Spain. Hyde recounts his travels to other countries.
  - C. Miscellaneous, 1910-1925 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Correspondents are General de Castelnau, Madame Colette, Edmond Clement, General Cadondal(?), M. Collignon, Yvonne Carteroux(?) of the Hospital de Madame Messimy.
  - Calmette, Gaston (editor of "Le Figaro"), 1902-1913 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cambon, Jules (2 folders), 1900-1928 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    The first folder contains extensive correspondence (in French); the second holds the program for the banquet held for Cambon (Ambassador of France) at Washington, DC, in 1902 by the Legionnaires in the United States (Hyde was on the Committee on Arrangements.)
  - Cambon, Paul, 1913-1921 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Capper, Arthur (U.S. Senator), 1925-1929 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Carrel, Alexis & Anne, 1913-1927 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Castellane, Boni & Anne de, 1906-1916 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Charmes, Francis, 1909-1913 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Chaumeix, Andre, 1910-1913 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Identified as editor of the Reveudes Deux Monds and a writer for the Journal des Debats.
  - Chinard, Gilbert, 1908-1921 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Chiappe, Jean, 1927-1935 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Clemenceau, Georges, 1915-1925 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clifton, Chalmers Dancy & Wanda B., 1919-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Extensive correspondence, in English, from Clifton commenting on U.S. politics, among other matters. Two programs from concerts conducted by Clifton (1929, 1933) are in the folder.
  - Coolidge, Archibald Cary (2 folders), 1896-1921 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    Several of the letters are addressed by Coolidge to a Monsieur Gofflot, at the same address used by Hyde and stamped as received by Hyde. These letters to Gofflot are in French; the other letters in this file are in English.
  - Coolidge, Harold Jefferson, 1902, 1928-1933 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Among other subjects, includes biographical note of Archibald Coolidge written by Hyde at brother Harold's request. Also includes a 1902 map of Indo-China marked to show Harold Coolidge's proposed area for traveling and collecting in 1928.
  - Coquelin [Cadet?], 1904-1909 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Although these letters certainly appear to be from Coquelin Cadet (i.e. Ernest Alexandre Honoré Coquelin), there is one letter signed "Coq" and stamped by Hyde as 1918, years after Coquelin's death. However, other correspondence in this series bears a similar stamped date, which often seems clear that it is a mistake and is actually 1908. One letter, from late 1909, is to Jean Coquelin. All other letters are from 1904-1907 or undated.
  - Cortesi, Salvatore, 1914-1931 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Principally concerns arrangements Hyde made through Cortesi to visit the Italian front in 1916, which led to an article written by Hyde.
  - Crane, Charles R, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cuyler, Thomas DeWitt (4 folders), 1899-1919 (Box 3, Folder 9-12)
    Principally concerns various business matters related to the Equitable Life Assurance Society (e.g., considering acquiring land in Philadelphia for an office adjacent to the Arcade Building at Broad and Market), Franklin National Bank, Commercial Trust Company, Girard Trust Company, National Union Bank, Citizens National Bank of Cincinnati, and others. These are often related to investments, acquisitions, bank consolidations, loans, board meeting arrangements and naming of directors. Most of the letters are incoming from Cuyler and date through 1904. There are fewer letters from 1906-1919, are mostly incoming from Cuyler with some outgoing from Hyde, and are generally pleasantries, with some references to financial matters.
  - D. Miscellaneous, 1898-1931 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Correspondents include, among others, Marcel Dieulafoy, Charles Dumon, J. Depelley, Monsieur Delcasse, J. Delton, Colonel Denvignes, General Henri Duport, General Debeny, Colonel Dupuy, and photo postcard of and from Warrington Dawson.
  - Dard, Emile, 1908-1920 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Deane, R, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Deering, James, 1903-1916 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Principally includes an invitation to Hyde to join the Franco-American Committee of Patronage, with material related to the organization (1903).
  - Depew, Chauncey M., 1892-1908 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Trustee of Equitable Trust Company and U.S. senator. Principally involves expressions of support and other matters consistent with a relationship between an older mentor from the business and political world and younger man attending Harvard and starting his career.
  - Deschanel, Paul (Mr & Mme), 1915-1919 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Diehl, Charles, 1926-1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Doumer, Paul, 1907, 1915-1930 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Doumergue, Gaston, 1925-1934 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Doumic, Rene & Helene, circa 1897-1913, 1927-1929 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Dubois (General), 1915 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - E. Miscellaneous, 1909-1935 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Correspondents are C. Enlart, Eugene d'Eichtal, Governor of Pennsylvania George H. Earle and wife Huberta.
  - Edge, Walter E., 1929-1931 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Concerns Ambassador Edge's initiative to acquire copies of portraits of past ambassadors to exhibit.
  - Einstein, Lewis, 1914, 1924-1930 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Primarily concerns exchanges (1924-25) regarding Hyde's and Einstein's tapestries, and others.
  - Estournelles de Constant (Baron), Jean d'Janvier, 1902-1913 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - F. Miscellaneous, 1902-1921 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Correspondents include, among others, Ambassador de Fleuriau, General Ferrie, General Feraud, David R. Francis (regarding the Louisiana Purchase Exposition Company), du Fonarre(?).
  - Fay, Bernard, 1920-1921, 1931-1934 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Ferrero, Guglielmo, 1908-1917, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Feuillerat, Albert, 1912-1931 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Finley, John Huston & Martha, 1911-1927 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Flat, Paul, 1915-1916 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Flers, Robert de, 1923, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Flexner, Abraham and Anne Crawford, 1912-1932 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Foch, Ferdinand (Maréchal & Mme) (3 folders), 1908-1931 (Box 4, Folder 17-19)
  - Forain, Jean Louis, 1906-1907 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Ford, J.D.M, 1921-1926 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Several letters written on stationery of American University Union in Europe for which Hyde and Ford were on the Continental Division's Executive Committee. Concerns various academic matters, including arrangements for Ford's lectures in Europe.
  - Ford, Stanley H., 1933 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Fortier, Alcee, 1902-1907 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Franchet d'Esperey (Maréchal), 1917-1918, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Francois, Marsal F., 1916 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Francois-Poncet, 1929-1931 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Friant, Emile, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Frick, Henry.Clay, 1901-1903 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Principally relates to bank relationships and shared directorships between Frick and Hyde.
  - Fullerton, W.M., 1911, 1914, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Includes, among other matters, discussion by Fullerton concerning arrangements for the Exposition internationale urbaine de Lyon in 1914.
  - Funck-Brentano, Frantz, 1900-1929 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Includes clippings about Funck-Brentano from 1900 and 1904. Letters begin in 1904.
  - G. Miscellaneous, 1916-1935 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Correspondents include, among others, General Charles Grant, Marcel Gounouilhou, General Gamelin, V. Grignard, General Gourko, General Georges, Sacha Guitry (and wife, Charlotte Lysis).
  - Gage, Homer (Doctor), 1927-1930 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    On the building of a dormitory for American students at Cite Universitaire in Paris.
  - Gardner, Isabella Stewart, 1908, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Several letters from Gardner, all but one undated. Generally appear to concern pleasantries, invitations, general references to Fenway Court, and other social matters.
  - Garner, James Wilford, 1917, 1920-1921 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Primarily concerns Garner's lecture tour in France (1921) and related matters.
  - Gay, Walter & Matilda (Mathilde), 1921-1924 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    All of the incoming letters are from Matilda Gay and concern various social matters and pleasantries. Includes a reference to pigeons acquired from Hyde for Le Briau.
  - Germain, Henri (Madame), 1903-1918 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Gibson, Hugh, 1922-1931 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Includes an invitation to Gibson's wedding (1922); letters concerning the arrangements and formalities for attending a Court Ball (1928), and a request by Hyde for a recommendation for a possible lecturer (1931).
  - Gillet, Louis, 1907-1934 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Giraudoux, Jean, 1907-1926 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Gould, Anna, 1906-1907 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Gouraud, Henri (General), 1911-1933 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Greene, Jerome D., 1899-1919 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Inquiries from Greene about a position with the Equitable (1899); letters of introduction from Greene; inquiries from Hyde as to Greene proposing him for club memberships; and other such matters.
  - Gregory, Eliot (2 folders), 1908-1915 (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
    Extensive correspondence discussing travels, lectures, cultural matters, social gossip, and personal observations on various matters.
  - Guillaumat (General), 1918 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Guitry, Lucien, 1920-1921 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - H. Miscellaneous, 1902-1904 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Only correspondent in the folder is G.G. Haven, concerning trusteeships and financial interests in banks.
  - Hale, Frederick, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Two letters from the U.S. senator from Maine in relation to American involvement in World War I.
  - Hallays, Andre, 1919-1925 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Hanotaux, Gabriel (Mr & Mme), 1912-1916, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Harbord, James G., 1917-1919 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Primarily concerns pleasantries and invitations.
  - Harjes, Henri H. & Ivy, 1916-1923 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    A request for Hyde to add his name to a draft request for funds and men for Red Cross ambulance units (draft included in file); request for Hyde to join a committee to present a monument to France commemorating the battle of the Marne; and Harjes's decline of an unidentified proposal by Hyde (1923).
  - Harper, William R., 1902 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Thank you letter for a donation to have guest lecturers.
  - Harrison, Alexander, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Harrison, Burton, 1893, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Harrison, Leland, 1921-1935 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1914, 1920-1926 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Concerns discussions over time regarding the possibility of Hart lecturing in France. The 1926 exchange includes Hyde's and Hart's perspectives on historical topics that are irritants in relations between America and France and would be best avoided in the lectures.
  - Harvard University (3 folders), 1908-1922, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 28-30)
    Correspondents include, among other, Henry Van Dyke, Charles W. Eliot, Waldron H. Rand, Jr., A. Lawrence Lowell, Archibald Cary Coolidge, C.H. Van Tyne, Jules Coulet, James W. Garner, and Henry Munroe. The principal topic concerns arrangements for Harvard to send various professors to lecture in France. These arrangements, especially in terms of the specific professors selected, involve both institutional and geopolitical considerations. There are some documents concerning related efforts, such as lecturers sent to Spain and a 1908 plan for English assistants to be placed in German schools. The bulk of the correspondence ends in 1922; two letters from 1935 include one from James B. Conant responding to Hyde's inquiry about plans for a committee in France for Harvard's 300th anniversary celebration. Some letters are to/from French correspondents and so are in French.
  - Harvard Exchange Professors, 1912, 1924, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes letters to and from Larz Anderson regarding forming a Harvard Club in Paris (1912) and letters to and from two French correspondents concerning arrangements for Harvard professors teaching in France.
  - Harvard - Instructeurs Militaires, 1909-1919 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Correspondents include, among others, E. Boutroux, Edward Benedic, Jerome Green, Jean Bourguignon, Carl Boyd, Francois de Chevigne, Jules Cambon.
  - Harvey, George, 1903, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Hastings, Thomas & Helen, 1906, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Concerns plans for a Marne battle monument in Paris.
  - Haumont, G., 1928-1931 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Hazard, Paul, 1914, 1922, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Hebrard, Adrien, 1908?-1914 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Helleu, Paul, 1921, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Henri-Robert (Maitre) (Attorney), 1909-1923 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Henrys (General), 1909-1911, 1918-1919 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Herbette, Louis, 1902-1907 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Herbette, Maurice & Denise, 1919-1920, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Herr, Georges (General), 1915-1932 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Herrick, Myron T. (3 folders), 1912-1929 (Box 6, Folder 14-16)
    Much of the correspondence dates from the periods during which Herrick was American ambassador to France.
  - Herriot, Edouard (Mr & Mme), 1912-1918 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Hervieu, Paul, 1909-1913 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Hills, Laurence, 1921-1933 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Hochon, Louise, 1907-1923, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Homolle, Theophile, 1908-1923 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Hopital Auxiliaire No. 79 (2 folders), 1915-1916 (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
    Documents concerning Hyde's Parisian home at 18 Rue Adolphe-Yvon, which he made available as an auxiliary hospital during World War I. Correspondents include the Societe Francaise de Secours aux Blesses Militaires, the American War Relief Clearing House, and many others. Much of the correspondence is from or directed to the administrator of the hospital; this is not Hyde, but L.V. Gofflot. Most of the documents are in French.
  - House, Edward M. (Colonel & Mme), 1902-1903, 1916-1933 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    Early correspondence concerns investments and directorships regarding Equitable. Also includes a preface written by Ernest Lavisse conncerning French heroism (1918), a proposal for an American Soldiers Memorial Hospital in France (circa 1920?), and other matters.
  - Humbert (General), 1918-1919 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Huntington, Archer & Helen, 1911-1926 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    Primarily letters of introduction, pleasantries and the like, though Hyde in one letter (1920) describes the route of his travels in Spain with some observations.
  - I. Miscellaneous, 1914-1930 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    Two correspondents: Issmett Riza Bey (1914) and General Issaly (1930)
  - Ishii, K (Ambassadeur), 1915, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Jaray, Gabriel Louis, 1910-1916, 1930-1932 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Joffre, Joseph and Henrietta, 1917-1929 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Jollivet, Gaston (Mr & Mme), 1912, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Jonnart, C, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Jouvenel, Henry & Colette de, 1914 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Jusserand, J.J. (Mr. & Mme), 1904-1928 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - K. Miscellaneous, 1907-1929 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Correspondents are Frau Krupp, L.L. Klotz, Henrietta King, Moustafa, Kamel Pacha.
  - Kahn, Otto H. & Addie (2 folders), 1900-1929 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    The documents from 1900-1909 primarily relate to the Conried Metropolitan Opera Company, the Metropolitan Opera, and the effort by Kahn and Hyde, among others, to develop a "New" or "National Theatre" in New York City. There are also references to Hyde in relation to the Equitable and his ownership of stock, letters of introduction, Hyde's travels in Asia and in Europe during the war, various social and investment matters, etc.
  - Kapurthala (Maharaja de), 1908-1919 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Kelly, Edmond, 1902-1904 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Kerney, James (2 folders), 1918-1933 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Knecht, Marcel, 1907-1922 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Knoblock, Edward (Edward Knoblauch), 1911-1931 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Knoblauch changes his surname to Knoblock in 1916. Early letters primarily concern a play of Knoblauch's. Later letters primarily concern art objects acquired by Hyde from Knoblock or with his advice.
  - Koechlin, Raymond, 1927-1930 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Kountze, William de Lancey, 1921-1922 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Kountze identifies art objects and requests Hyde's help in acquiring information about them, which Hyde agrees to.
  - L. Miscellaneous, 1904-1933 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Correspondents are R. de Lamerzan, Rene Lara, Monseigneur Le Roy, Le Coz, Edward Loftus, Louis Loucheur (one letter to James Kerney), H. livington-Sampson, A. de Laborde, Andre de Laboublaye, A.T. Long, Philip M. Lydig (concerning purchasing shares of the Metropolitan Opera Company), Sylvain Lears(?), E.A. Leblond(?), and Le Vert Coleman.
  - Labbe, Paul, 1917, 1925-1935 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Labori (Maitre), 1903-1904 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Lacaze, L. (Admiral), 1915-1926 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Lacour-Gayet, Georges, 1911-1924 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Lagrave, Michel, 1902-1903 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Lamont, Thomas W., 1919-1921 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Concerns funding of the monument of the Battle of the Marne, to be sculpted by Frederick William MacMonnies.
  - Lamy, Etienne, 1911-1914 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Langlois, Ch.V., 1921(?), 1929 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Lanson, Gustave, 1913-1929 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Lapeyrere, Boue de (Amiral), 1914, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Lapie, Paul, 1913, 1925-1926 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Lauzanne, Stephane, 1916-1927 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Lavedan, Henri (Mr & Mme), 1914-1929 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Lavisse, Ernest, 1908-1921 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    See also the Edward House folder for a piece written by Lavisse.
  - Le Braz, Anatole, 1904-1923 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Lebrun, Albert (Senateur), 1921-1927 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Lecomte, Georges, 1909-1918 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Lee, Ivy L., 1919-1920 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Lefranc, Abel, 1908-1925 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Legouis, Emile, 1913, 1918, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Leland, Waldo G., 1924-1925 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    Primarily concerns Leland's suggestions for funding and donation of materials for libraries at French universities, and for an exchange of professorships, both involving Harvard. Includes Hyde's detailed notes of a discussion between him and Leland on these subjects.
  - Lenotre, G., 1904-1906 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Le Roux, Hugues (Mr & Mme), 1900-1904 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    Among other documents, includes two picture postcard of Le Roux "presente a Menelik la carte du Nil Bleu."
  - LeRoy, Lewis H. (Colonel), 1917 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Leroy-Beaulieu, Anatole (Mr & Mme), 1903-1911 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - LeRoy, White J., 1902-1910 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Liard, L., 1906-1913 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Loubet, Emile (Mr & Mme), 1900-1912 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Low, Seth, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Concerning lectures on life insurance to be given at Columbia.
  - Luchaire, Julien, 1913-1931 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Lyautey (Maréchal), 1909-1933 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Lyon, Georges, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Lythgoe, Albert, 1925-1926 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Concerns Hyde's donation to the Metropolitan Museum of Art,specifically in regard to support for Lythgoe's archaelogical work in Egypt. Lythgoe refers to some aspects of arrangements for the work. See also Edward Robinson folder below.
  - M. Miscellaneous, 1904-1931 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Correspondents McDougall Hawkes, General de Maud'Huy, Robert H. McCurdy, Langdon P. Marvin, Maurice Muret, Edwin H. Morgan, L'Abbe A. Mugnier, Le Contre-Amiral Mornet, General Meunier, G. Macon, Baron de Meslon, Henry Morgenthau, Prince Danilo de Montenegro, F.A. Mahan, Daniel Michend(?), Monsieur Mauricheau-Beaupre.
  - Mabilleau, Leopold, 1902-1904 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Mackay, Clarence & Katherine, 1903-1909, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Principally concerns activities related to the founding of a "National Theatre" in New York and Hyde's sale of his shares in the Metropolitan Opera Company to Mackay (1906-09). Also concerns Mackay buying shares in Equitable (1903) and other cultural matters (1927).
  - MacMonnies, Frederick, 1920, 1923, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Primarily concerns MacMonnies acquiring a letter of introduction to see Marshal Foch, the Battle of the Marne monument, and pleasantries.
  - McCook, John J., 1878, 1904, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    McCook forwards in 1904 an original 1878 memorandum written by Hyde's father concerning "Mutual's reduction in rates." The 1910 letter from McCook is a letter of reference for a Mr. Straus.
  - McCormick, Harold F., 1920s? (Box 8, Folder 16)
    Holds a single document: a statement surveying the history and recent prospects of the International Harvester Company in relation to its business activities in France, possibly in connection with granting a national honor to McCormick.
  - McCormick, Medill, 1918,1920 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    US Senator from Illinois. Declined to speak in France due to concerns about the French public's sentiment toward American relations.
  - McCurdy, Richard A., 1901-1903 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    McCurdy was president of the Mutual Life Insurance Company of New York. Though the references are somewhat obscure, the letters from McCurdy appear to concern bank investments and acquisitions for Mutual and the Equitable. Concerning growth of the Continental Insurance Company.
  - Madelin, Louis, 1907-1928 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Mahon, Patrice (Commandat & Madame), 1900-1912, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Maklakoff, M. (Marie and Basile), 1921-1929 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Male, Emile, 1920, 1927-1928, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    Also includes correspondence with Georges Guiraud.
  - Mangin, Ch. (General & Madame), 1917-1919, undated (Box 8, Folder 23)
    Also includes two calling cards of Mr. MacMonnies, with written notes.
  - Manoury, H., 1914-1917 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Manzoni, G. (Comte), 1927, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Marbury, Elisabeth (Miss), 1903-1909, 1919-1920 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    Early letters concern possible productions of plays. Later letters relate to Marbury seeking Hyde's assistance in receiving the Legion of Honor.
  - Marriner, J.T. (James Theodore), 1933 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    Concerns the possibility of erecting a statue to the Marquis de Rochambeau, and a letter of introduction.
  - Martet, Jean, 1917-1918 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Martin, Germain, 1902-1933 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Martin, R. William, 1915-1918 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Matsui, K. (Mr & Mme), 1916-1919 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Maurois, Andre, 1926-1933 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    Among other matters, list of names and meetings for Maurois in connection with his trip to America.
  - Menier, Gaston, 1911-1912, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Metman, Louis, 1921-1930 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Meyer, Arthur, 1910, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Michel, Andre (Mr & Mme), 1903-1908 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Mierry, Jean de (Commandant), 1921-1931 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Millerand, Alexandre (Mr & Mme), 1906-1932 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Millet, Rene, 1904-1911 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Mitchell, William (General), 1917-1927 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Photographic Negative of Unidentified Object, Undated (Box 8, Folder 41)